Louis J. Budd Papers and compilation of Mark Twain Resources, 1980-2008, undated
Elmira College
Louis J. Budd Papers and compilation of Mark Twain Resources, 1980-2008, undated
The bulk of the papers are comprised of Lou Budd’s collection of Mark Twain caricatures, interviews and reviews. Correspondence and materials related to his tenure as trustee at the Mark Twain Memorial for the years 1992-1999 are the extent of materials in the collection related to Budd’s professional life. The collection contains the manuscript and research for one scholarly article, Seeing Double Can be Twice as Clear: Mark Twain’s Impersonators.
6.42 Linear ft. (6 Cartons, 1 Hollinger Box)
Budd, Louis J.
Mark Twain Archive, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
unrestricted
Budd was born August 26, 1921 in St. Louis, Missouri, the last of three children in his family. His father Vincent Budrewicz, a Polish immigrant from Lithuania, had served in the army of Czarist Russia.
When discharged as a reservist, Vincent Budrewicz emigrated, arriving in America in 1910. Louis's mother Zofia Kajszo, a devout Catholic, emigrated from Lithuania to America in 1911. In 1930 Vincent Budrewicz was a laborer in a shoe factory and his wife Zofia worked at a bakery a half a block from the family home. Following the lead of his older brother, Louis would later change his surname to Budd.
After graduating from high school at age fifteen, Budd attended the University of Missouri majoring in English literature and was elected to Phi Beta Kappa. Budd received his B.A. there in 1941 and his M.A. in 1942.
After serving in World War II, in 1945 he married Isabelle Amelia Marx-it was a marriage that produced two children and lasted more than 60 years, until her death in 2006. Budd entered the University of Wisconsin under the GI Bill and obtained his Ph.D. in American literature in 1949. Budd's doctoral thesis was titled "William Dean Howells's Relations with Political Parties."
From 1949 to 1952, Budd taught at the University of Kentucky at Lexington. In 1952 he relocated to Duke University and remained with Duke until his retirement. Budd's first book titled "Mark Twain: Social Philosopher" was published by Indiana University Press in 1962. The book traced the development of Mark Twain's social commitments and changing political attitudes.
Budd received a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1965. He lectured in India in May 1966 as a Fulbright scholar and returned to lecture in India again in October and November of 1972.
From 1968-70 he chaired the Afro-American Studies program at Duke. In 1973 he became chairman of the English department and served in that capacity until 1979. In June of 1978 Budd traveled to the University of Damascus as a visiting lecturer. He was awarded a NEH Senior Fellowship in 1979-80. In 1979 he became managing editor of the journal American Literature. Budd became a prolific editor with Duke University Press, publishing numerous literary collections taken from back issues of American Literature.
He served on editorial and advisory boards of numerous publications including Studies in American Humor, South Atlantic Review, Mississippi Studies in English, and American Literary Realism.
Throughout his career, Budd used his archival research skills to compile data on Mark Twain. In 1983, Budd published "Our Mark Twain: The Making of His Public Personality," which included rare caricatures and cartoons of Twain gathered from scarce 19th century publications.
Budd was the recipient of numerous awards for outstanding scholarship, including several honorary degrees. In 1991 Budd received one of the first Mark Twain Circle Awards.
Budd formally retired from Duke University in 1991 although he continued to teach there until 1996. In 1992 he arranged and annotated a two-volume edition "Mark Twain: Collected Tales, Sketches, Speeches, & Essays" for Library of America. In 1999 Budd published "Mark Twain: The Contemporary Reviews" with Cambridge University Press which provided hard-to- obtain texts of early magazine and newspaper reviews of Mark Twain's works. In 2005 he and Peter Messent co-edited "A Companion to Mark Twain."
Budd, Louis J.; Caricatures and cartoons; Facsimiles; Legislative materials; Photography--Negatives; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910; Personal correspondence
The collection is primarily a compilation of resources compiled by Lou Budd regarding Mark Twain caricatures, interviews and reviews. The caricatures, interviews and reviews are secondary sources consisting of reproductions, transcriptions, negatives and prints.
The collection contains research and manuscript drafts for one article titled, “Seeing Double Can Be Twice as Clear: Mark Twain Impersonators.” Budd’s affiliation with the Mark Twain Memorial as Trustee is represented in the collection through board minutes, agendas and correspondence, including news clippings, articles and promotional materials regarding Mark Twain’s Hartford house.
Absent from the collection are personal papers or documents pertinent to Lou Budd’s scholarship.
- SERIES 1: PROFESSIONAL PAPERS, 1979 - 1999
  - SUB-SERIES 1: MARK TWAIN MEMORIAL TRUSTEES MATERIALS, 1992 - 1999; This sub-series contains information gathered by Louis Budd as a trustee of the Mark Twain Memorial. The bulk of the material pertains to board related activities, including newsletters, clippings and promotional materials. This series is organized alphabetically and chronologically by folder title.
    - Board of Trustees -- Correspondence, agendas, minutes, etc., 1992 - 1993
    - Board of Trustees -- Correspondence, agendas, minutes, clippings, 1994 - 1995
    - Board of Trustees -- Louis Budd Comments [manuscript, 1994
    - Board of Trustees -- Reports, 1994
    - Board of Trustees -- Correspondence, agendas, minutes, 1996 - 1998
    - News articles, 1989 - 1996
    - Newsletters -- Mark Twain News, 1993 - 1999
    - Promotional Materials, 1992 - 1997
  - SUB-SERIES 2: MANUSCRIPT MATERIALS, 1982 - 1997; This sub-series contains research, correspondence and drafts for a paper titled, “Seeing Double Can Be Twice as Clear: Mark Twain Impersonators.” These folders remain in original order.
    - Mark Twain Doubles (1) -- Edited manuscript, "Seeing Double Can Be Twice as Clear: Mark Twain's Impersonators," clippings, correspondence, 1997
    - Mark Twain Doubles (2) -- Edited manuscript, "Seeing Double Can be Twice as Clear: Mark Twain's Impersonators," clippings, correspondence, offprint, 1995 - 1996
    - Mark Twain Doubles (3) -- Research materials on Twain impersonators, includes clippings, correspondence, photograph, 1990 - 1994
    - Mark Twain Doubles (4) -- Research materials on Twain impersonators, includes clippings, articles, correspondence, 1983 - 1989
    - Mark Twain Doubles (5) -- Research materials on Twain impersonators, includes clippings, articles, correspondence, 1982 - 1983
  - SUB-SERIES 3: PROPOSALS AND PAPERS, 1979 - 1999; This sub-series contains no works by Lou Budd and is primarily comprised of proposals for Mark Twain related programming, particularly for television, that were sent to Budd. The scripts for Samuel Clemens and Mark Twain a film project by Sandra Bradley and Mark Twain and Mark Twain and the Laughing River by Jim Post are the only materials in this sub-series that contain correspondence whereby Budd offers an opinion on the work. All other files only contain the article and/or project proposal. This series is organized alphabetically by title.
    - Life on the Mississippi -- TV script by Philip Reisman, 1979
    - Mark Twain: Beneath the Laughter: A Discussion Leader's Guide, undated
    - Mark Twain: Cradle Skeptic ---Wesley Britton typescript, 1998
    - Mark Twain and the Laughing River -- Includes photographs, correspondence between Budd and Post about the review of the play, 1997 - 1999
    - Mark Twain and Me -- Article by Barry Crimmins from the Cleveland Plain Dealer, 1997
    - Mark Twain Series -- NEH proposal, 1979
    - Mark Twain's Adventures of Huckleberry Finn: Humor and Race, A Callback Session on Teaching the Novel in High Schools -- By David E. E. Sloane, 1995
    - Mark Twain's Bizarre Shorts -- Pandora's Players script, 1983
    - The Private History of A Campaign that Failed and The War Prayer -- TV script by Philip Reisman, 1980
    - Sam Clemens and Mark Twain -- Film proposal by Sandra Bradley, 1995
    - Sam Clemens: Inventing Mark Twain -- Treatment and Script, 1994
    - Sam Clemens: Inventing Mark Twain -- Correspondence, includes part III script, 1993 - 1995
- SERIES 2: CARICATURES, 1980 - 2008; The series primarily consists of reproductions, negatives and prints of Mark Twain caricatures. Louis Budd states in a letter to the National Portrait Gallery in 1989, “For some years I have been gathering caricatures of Mark Twain, especially those done during his lifetime. Eventually, of course, I plan some kind of publication though I am still primarily concerned with gathering and analyzing the materials” (Box 2 Folder 182). Caricatures from later dates, though present, are not as thoroughly documented. The collection contains few original materials and is almost exclusively comprised of prints and negatives of reproductions. Dates from the limited correspondence and from Budd’s online resources, including the statement above, indicate Budd was actively collecting caricatures for an eventual publication up until his death in 2006. The collection is primarily focused on caricatures created in Twain’s own time; caricatures from later dates, though present, are not as thoroughly documented. This series represents Budd’s twenty plus year research commitment to collecting Mark Twain caricatures. The collection of Mark Twain caricatures remains in original order, primarily organized by date of publication (the first three folders are miscellaneous). Original folder headings are used whenever possible.
  - Mark Twain Association -- photocopied articles and notes about the association, 1997 - 1999
  - Memo on Tom Quirk -- Inventory of cartoon folders sent to Tom Quirk, 2001
  - Innocents Abroad -- Letter and photocopied title page; Mark Twain with tomahawk, 1981
  - Mark Twain "Funny Baby"; caricature, 1870's with letter, 1997
  - "Once a Week", 14 December, 1872: Mark Twain astride a frog, undated
  - "Mark Twain's Funniest Fiction Fully Illustrated", early 1870's: Mark Twain as Jester, 2003
  - Illustrations for Roughing It / Mark Twain Lecturing, undated
  - "Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper," 26 July, 1873, undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 15 November, 1873: Mark Twain Cap and Bells, "The Lyceum Committeeman's Dream", undated
  - "American Publisher": Mark Twain at Tomb of Adam, undated
  - Mark Twain lecturing in England 1873?, undated
  - A Hoppin -- C. d. Warren, "Backlog Studies", undated
  - New York, 26 October, 1874 and 1876: Theodore Wust illustration of Mark Twain platform pose, undated
  - Mark Twain weeping at Tomb of Adam [transparency], undated
  - F. D. Millet Portrait c. 1896, undated
  - "Suggestions about Work" 1880's?, undated
  - Mark Twain attends Ingersoll Lecture, "Chic," May 1881, undated
  - Harper's Weekly, 21 January 1882, Thomas Nast, Mark Twain in Canada in search of Copyright, undated
  - Life, 22 March 1883: Mark Twain holding skull, undated
  - Life, 9 August 1883: Mark Twain sleeping in chair, undated
  - Clover Club, 9 April 1885 -- profile portrait, with correspondence, 1998
  - Commercial Gazette, Cincinnati, 26 September 1885, undated
  - "Mark Twain's Funniest Fiction Fully Illustrated" -- Cap and Bells, c. 1885, undated
  - "Puck," 16 December 1885 -- Artist Joseph Keppler: Mark Twain on Platform, undated
  - "Puck," 24 February 1886 -- International Copyright, Mark Twain in Chorus of British Authors, undated
  - "Boston Sunday Globe," 3 July 1887, undated
  - "St. Louis Post-Dispatch," 11 December 1887 -- caricature, undated
  - "New York World," 11 November 1888: Mark Twain and Browning (Bill Rye's Column), undated
  - "New York World," 9 April 1889: Baseball cartoon, undated
  - "St. Louis Post-Dispatch," 19 May 1889 -- "Mark Twain Writing Under Difficulties", undated
  - "New York World," 16 June 1889: "Mark Twain at Work", undated
  - "New York World," 16 June 1889: "Mark Twain at Work", undated
  - "Critic, 45," 4 October 1890 -- Mark Twain self-portrait with Laurence Hutton, undated
  - "Life," 27 February 1890: Twain wearing dress and holding cat [transparency, undated
  - "Idler," February 1892: Mark Twain blowing soap bubbles, 1990
  - Theodore Wust -- Correspondence about "The Interrupted Siesta," 1890's, 1980
  - "Idler," October, 1892 ": Mark Twain in Quaker City, undated
  - "Life," three faked photographs, February 1895, undated
  - Notecards containing information about published caricatures of Mark Twain, undated
  - "Puck," 10 July 1895: "Great Speech by McKinley", undated
  - "New York World," 12 July 1895, undated
  - "A Lifetime with Mark Twain; the memories of Katy Leary...": "Mark Twain at Home"[, undated
  - Sydney (Australia) Bulletin, 28 September 1895: Mark Twain and Henry Parkes, undated
  - Five cartoons copied from Shillingsburg MS, "Abroad: Mark Twain in Australasia," 1895, undated
  - Sydney (NSW) Bulletin, 5 October 1895 -- Tom Burkin Sketch, undated
  - Melbourne Australia, October 1895: Mark Twain Smoke Night, undated
  - London Sketch, 27 November 1895: Mark Twain on Platform, undated
  - "Life," 28 May 1896: Mark Twain as Joan of Arc by F. T. Richards -- transparency, undated
  - "Book Buyer," February 1897 ": Mark Twain with Puppet Characters, undated
  - "Life," 4 February 1897, NYC newspaper scene; "Life's School of Journalism, undated
  - "Life," 27 May 1897: Mark Twain on Boat -- Transparency, undated
  - Vienna Erfloh: Mark Twain as Diogenes and other Dolmetsch cartoons, 1897, undated
  - "New York Journal and Advertiser," 21 November 1897: Mark Twain at Vienna Press Club, includes transparency, undated
  - "New York World," 13 December 1897, Mark Twain Addressing Vienna Press Club, undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 1 March 1898: Mark Twain speaking German verse, includes transparency, undated
  - "Life," 26 May 1898: Mark Twain caricature, undated
  - "Life," 18 August 1898: Portrait caricature, "Eyes that 'lack only the nictating membrane of the eagle', undated
  - Book illustration, 1898: "The boy chieftain knelt and kissed the hem of the maiden's robe," American Literary Realism, vol. 8 no. 2, 1975, undated
  - "Criterion," 18 February 1899: unconventional statues-V, undated
  - "Life," 2 March 1899: Twain caricature, "The American Humorist", undated
  - "Criterion," 18 February 1899: Mark Twain: unconventional statues-V: Mark Twain could make a sphinx laugh, undated
  - "Boston Herald," 15 June 1899: Mark Twain as Internal Raconteur -- photograph and transparency, undated
  - "New York World," 6 August 1899: "Mark Twain before Breakfast" -- photograph and transparency, undated
  - "New York World," 10 December 1899: Mark Twain looking through binoculars, includes transparency, undated
  - "An Alphabet of Celebrities" by Oliver Herford, 1899: caricature, includes transparency, undated
  - "An impromptu by Phil May," June 1900, "The Savage Club" by Aaron Watson, undated
  - "Metropolitan Magazine," 12 July 1900 " -- Twentieth Century Cartoons," by Will Hudson, undated
  - "New York World," 21 October 1900: "A First Impression of Mark Twain", undated
  - "Independent," 25 October 1900 by P. Bigelow: "Mark Twain Addressing a Committee of the House of Lords on International Copyright, undated
  - "New York Herald," 23 November 1900: "Mark Twain Talks of Cabmen to Mayor's Marshal Roch," includes transparency, undated
  - "Puck," 5 December 1900, Frank Nankivell: Caricature, undated
  - "Louisville Times," 14 December 1900: Caricature, undated
  - "New York Commercial Advertisers," 22 December 1900: "Mark Twain and His Empire -- A Laughing World", undated
  - F. C. Gould, 1901-1903?: Caricature, undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 5 February 1901, by F. Opper, Mark Twain and McKinley, undated
  - "Syracuse Herald," 5 February 1901: "The Kicking Joker", undated
  - Minneapolis Tribune, 14 February 1901 -- "Better quit your foolin', Mark, and go back and work at your trade -- Twain holding elephants tail with 'politics' written on its side, undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 23 February 1901: "Having the Time of His Life" -- Twain getting hit by snowballs, undated
  - "Life," 28 February 1901: "The American Lion CF St. Mark's,": Twain caricature as lion, includes letter for permission to copy, 2004
  - "Minneapolis Tribune," 20 March 1901 -- "The Best Joke Yet" --includes transparency, undated
  - "Minneapolis Journal," 23 March 1901: "Can the Missionary Reach This Old Savage" -- Twain caricature as savage, undated
  - "New York World," 25 March 1901: "With Poets as Policemen Mark Twain Would Purify the City," transparency, undated
  - "Kansas City Journal," 29 April 1901: Mark Twain pulled in cart by N.Y. Clerical Union, undated
  - "Judge," 11 May 1901 --includes transparency and photograph, undated
  - "Bookman," September 1901, by Tim Murphy: "A Man of Mark" caricature -- includes transparency, undated
  - "St. Louis Republic," 16 October 1901: "Mark Twain will fight Tammany [Tiger]", undated
  - Mark Twain as Yachtsman(?) by Harry Furness, 1902?, undated
  - "Pastel," by Everett Shinn, 1902: Mark Twain sitting, "Portrait of Mark Twain, undated
  - "New York Herald," 23 February 1902: Mark Twain sitting at desk writing, "Mark Twain in an Engrossing Moment", undated
  - "St. Louis Republic," 2 June 1902: "Mark Twain at Hannibal", undated
  - "St. Louis Republic," 7 June 1902: "Mark Twain as Pilot on Mississippi's Bosom", undated
  - "St. Louis Republic," 8 June 1902 " Mark Twain in St. Louis, undated
  - Advertisement for Alfred Houghton Clark pastel portraits, including Mark Twain, November 1902, undated
  - "New York World" 23 November 1902: Mark Twain self-portrait and "The audience broke into uncontrollable laughter", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 20 December 1902: "Homer Davenport's Impressions of Twain", undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 7 February 1903: "The Man Who Corrupted Eddyville, undated
  - "Booklovers Magazine," March 1903: Mark Twain with Halo "Fame", undated
  - "Strand," May 1903: Mark Twain Speaking, undated
  - "Booklovers Magazine," June 1903: Mark Twain Lecturing, undated
  - "Bookman," July 1903: "Our artist makes two farewell sketches of Mark Twain," include transparency
  - "St. Nicholas," September 1903: caricature, with transparency, undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 1903: "Mark Twain retranslating the jumping frog from French", undated
  - "Life," 24 December 1903: "The Brave Sir Mark: A Yankee Writer at King Arthur's Court," transparency, undated
  - Mark Twain illustration for "Esquimau Maiden's Romance," in Autograph Edition, 1903, undated
  - "The Art of Caricature," 1904 --transparency, photograph, undated
  - "Bystander," by Thus. Downey, 17 February 1904, undated
  - "Mark Twain and Max O'Rell" by Harry Furness, 1904, undated
  - "Puck," 1 March 1905: Mark Twain as Newfoundland Dog, includes transparency, undated
  - "Life," 13 July 1905: "Mark Twain Pilot" transparency, undated
  - "Chicago Tribune," 6 December 1905; caricature by John T. McCutcheon, undated
  - "New York World" 6 December 1905: "Honored Humorist with Incidents in His Career, From Youth up to Threescore Years and Ten", undated
  - Mark Twain with Halo by Robert Reid, 6 December 1905, undated
  - "Spokane Spokesman Review,"8 December 1905 by Morris: "Here's Hoping He'll Make the Hundred Mark", undated
  - "New York Herald," 10 December 1905, Third Section, Page 4: "When Author's Passed in Proud Review", undated
  - Cass Gilbert, 1905 or else latter [sic], undated
  - "Life," 21 December 1905: "His 70th Birthday", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 22 December 1905: A Bradshaw caricature, undated
  - "New York World," 4 February 1906 -- "The Press Club will send a wheelbarrow for Mark Twain," includes transparency, undated
  - "New York American," 9 March 1906: A Bradshaw caricature, undated
  - "New York World," 13 April 1906: Dethroning Czar, undated
  - "Life," 5 July 1906 -- Transparency, undated
  - "New York Times," 2 September 1906 -- "The Caricature of Himself that Mark Twain Liked Best", undated
  - "New York American," 20 September 1906 -- Includes transparencies and photographs of two caricatures, undated
  - "New York Times," 20 September 1906 -- Caricature as infant, undated
  - "New York World," 25 November 1906 -- Twain at party, includes transparency and photograph, undated
  - "New York World," 8 December 1906 -- "Mark Twain in that Cream Colored Suit," includes transparency and photograph, undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 22 December 1906: Writing his Autobiography, undated
  - Frederic Remington, c. 1906, undated
  - "Life," 31 January 1907 -- Transparency, undated
  - "New York Herald," 15 February 1907 -- "Mark Twain has suit of white for evening wear", undated
  - "St. Paul Pioneer Press," 17 February 1907 -- "Mark Twain in evening dress; sketched from telegraphic description", undated
  - "Saturday Evening Mail," 23 February 1907, undated
  - "Boston Post," 24 February 1907, p. 33 -- "Mark Twain in his Suit of White, undated
  - "Puck," 24 March 1907 -- no image, undated
  - "New York World," 7 May 1907 --" Persons prominent at Fair for the Benefit of Actors' Fund -- World Booth", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 7 May 1907 -- "Mark Twain in His Justly Celebrated White Flannel Suite made the Opening Speech", undated
  - "Baltimore News," 11 May 1907, p. 9: "Sketches of Mark Twain", undated
  - "London Daily Chronicle," 19 June 1907: P. Richards -- "Mark Twain on Board the Minneapolis", undated
  - "Puck," 19 June 1907 -- "The way he will get it: Oxford University will confer an honorary degree on Mark Twain next week", undated
  - "London Chronicle," 20 June 1907: D. Watson, "Mr Clemens and the Marked Twain", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 20 June 1907, undated
  - "Minneapolis Journal," 21 June 1907: "The Connecticut Yankee in King Edwards Court", undated
  - "New York Globe and Commercial Advertiser," 21 June 1907: Mark Twain in Bathrobe, undated
  - "New York American," 22 June 1907: Mark Twain in Bathrobe, undated
  - "St. Paul Pioneer Press," 22 June 1907: "King Full on Deuces", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 24 June 1907: Mark Twain and Fedinck and King, undated
  - "St. Louis Democrat," 24 June 1907 -- King Edward had a hearty laugh over a joke Mark Twain made 35 years ago", undated
  - "Columbus (Ohio) Evening Dispatch," 25 June 1907: Mark Twain jokes with Queen of England, undated
  - Pilgrims Luncheon, 25 June 1907, undated
  - "London Daily Graphic," 26 June 1907 -- "Honouring the Greatest Living Author", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 26 June 1907 -- "A Surgical Operation" drawn by Phil May, undated
  - "New York Herald," 26 June 1907: RE: Punch Cartoon -- "England's Homage to Mark Twain; Notables at Pilgrims' Luncheon", undated
  - "Life," 27 June 1907, undated
  - "Chicago Daily Tribune," 28 June 1907: A Good Story by Briggs, undated
  - "Onlooker," 29 June 1907 -- "More Tramps Abroad", undated
  - "Washington Evening Star," 29 June 1907 -- By Berryman, undated
  - "New York Times," 30 June 1907 -- "Mark Twain in London" by Hy. Mayer, undated
  - "Yankee in Court of King Edward," Seattle Spokesman Review, July-August, 1907, undated
  - "New York Press," 5 July 1907, undated
  - "Jabberwock," 6 July 1907: Winning Post, undated
  - "Savage Club House Dinner," 6 July 1907, undated
  - Westminster Gazette, 8 July 1907: "Mark Twain's Real Jumping Frog", undated